Inventory of the Theodore Fred Abel papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Incremental Materials, 1932-1988
  - Speeches and writings, 1933-1986
    - "Sociology in Postwar Poland,", 1950
      Box/Folder 25: 10
    - Review of Social Behavior and Personality edited by Edmund H. Volkart, circa 1951
      Box/Folder 25: 11
    - "The Sociology of Concentration Camps,", 1951
      Box/Folder 25: 12
    - Review of Vanguard of Nazism by Robert G. L. Waite, circa 1952
      Box/Folder 25: 13
    - Review of Contemporary Social Reform Movements edited by John Eric Nordskorg, circa 1954
      Box/Folder 25: 14
    - Review of Sociological Theory by Nicholas S. Timasheff, 1955
      Box/Folder 25: 15
    - Review of Polish Immigrants in Britain by Jerzy Zubrzycki and The Hague by Martinus Nijhoff, circa 1956
      Box/Folder 25: 16
    - "Eastern Sociological Society Dinner,", 1957
      Box/Folder 25: 17
    - Review of The Paradox of Progressive Thought by David W. Noble, circa 1958
      Box/Folder 25: 18
    - Review of The Sociology of Knowledge by Werner Stark, circa 1958
      Box/Folder 25: 19
    - Review of The Nature and Types of Sociological Theory, 1961
      Box/Folder 25: 20
    - Review of The Problem of Social Scientific Knowledge by William P. McEwen, circa 1963
      Box/Folder 25: 21
    - "On the Nazi Movement,", 1964
      Box/Folder 25: 22
    - Review of The Uses of Comparative Sociology by Stanislaw Andreski, circa 1965
      Box/Folder 25: 23
    - "Nature of Theory,", 1966
      Box/Folder 25: 24
    - Review of Social Relations and Social Roles by Florian Znaniecki, 1966
      Box/Folder 25: 25
    - "Basis of Personal Optimism,", 1967
      Box/Folder 25: 26
    - "Basis of Personal Optimism,", circa 1967
      Box/Folder 25: 27
    - Review of The Concept of Equilibrium in American Social Thought by Cynthia Eagle Russett, 1967
      Box/Folder 25: 28
    - Review of Social Change and History by Robert A. Nisbet, circa 1969-1970
      Box/Folder 25: 29
      Includes notes on theories of social change.
    - "Comments by a Sociologist (Theodore Abel),", 1970
      Box/Folder 25: 30
    - Review of A Sociology of Sociology by Robert W. Friedrichs, 1970
      Box/Folder 25: 31
    - "On Sociological Theory,", 1971
      Box/Folder 25: 32
    - "On the Use of Subjective Factors,", 1971
      Box/Folder 25: 33
    - "Some Preliminary Remarks on the Future of Sociological Theory,", 1974
      Box/Folder 25: 34
    - Abstract for Verstehen I and Verstehen II, 1975
      Box/Folder 25: 35
    - Writings on subjective factors, 1975, undated
      Box/Folder 25: 36
    - "Reflections on the Future of Social Problems Theory: On Humanistic Society,", 1976
      Box/Folder 25: 37
    - Review of Sociology: A Multiple Paradigm Science by George Ritzer, 1976
      Box/Folder 25: 38
    - Letter to the editor in Christian Sociologists Newsletter, 1977
      Box/Folder 25: 39
    - "On a Problem of Social Change,", 1978
      Box/Folder 25: 40
    - Review of The Family Crucible by Augustus Y. Napier and Carl A. Whitaker, 1978
      Box/Folder 25: 41
    - "Yukio Mishima,", 1978
      Box/Folder 25: 42
      Written by Theodora Abel, with the assistance of Theodore Abel.
    - Review of The War Path by David Irving and The Bunker by James P. O'Donnell, 1979
      Box/Folder 25: 43
    - "On the Origin of Life,", circa 1980
      Box/Folder 25: 44
    - "On Women,", 1981
      Box/Folder 25: 45
    - Review of Generations and Politics: A Panel Study of Young Adults and Their Parents by M. Kent Jennings and Richard G. Niemi, circa 1981
      Box/Folder 25: 46
    - "The Polish Immigrant in a New England Farming Community,", 1983
      Box/Folder 25: 47
    - "Reflections on James McKeever's You Can Overcome,", 1983
      Box/Folder 25: 48
    - "My Youth,", 1984
      Box/Folder 25: 49
    - "Prolegomenon to a Theory of Social Planning,", circa 1984
      Box/Folder 25: 50
    - "U.S. Economic Crisis Looms," editorial, 1984
      Box/Folder 25: 51
    - Review of American Freedom and the Social Sciences by James Deese, circa 1985
      Box/Folder 25: 52
    - "The Reflections of an Unorthodox Christian,", 1986
      Box/Folder 25: 53
  - Course material and notes, 1932-1986
    Includes lecture notes, a teaching evaluation of Abel, course handouts, and notes by subject. Arranged alphabetically by format.
    - Course handouts and notes on sociology concepts and definitions, 1950-1974, undated (Reel 22)
      Box/Folder 26: 1
      Includes materials from courses at Hunter College and the University of New Mexico.
    - Evaluation of Theodore Abel by students, 1932
      Box/Folder 26: 2
    - Hunter College project plan to establish a coeducational, graduate school of social work, undated
      Box/Folder 26: 3
    - Lecture notes on radical antagonism, undated
      Box/Folder 26: 4
    - Lecture outlines and notes for 1975 semester, 1972-1975, undated
      Box/Folder 26: 5
    - List of books donated to University of New Mexico library, 1971
      Box/Folder 26: 6
    - Miscellany, undated
      Box/Folder 26: 7
    - Notes on Max Weber, Spring semester, 1965
      Box/Folder 26: 8
      See also: Subject file, Max Weber (Box 27, Folders 5-6) and Note on writings and predictions (Box 24, Folder 8).
    - Notes, undated
      Box/Folder 26: 9-10
    - Notes, 1936-1974
      Box/Folder 26: 11
      Includes Verstehen notes and writings.
    - Reading lists, syllabi, and exam instructions, 1940-1970
      Box/Folder 26: 12
      Includes materials for courses at Columbia University.
    - Subject file
      Mainly notes, most likely including notes for lectures. Includes writings by Abel, printed matter, and course materials.
      - General, 1960-1986
        Box/Folder 26: 13
      - 19th century, 1959-1973 (Reel 23)
        Box/Folder 27: 1
      - Causation, free will, design, 1935-1976
        Box/Folder 27: 2
      - German militarism, World War II, 1943-1951, undated
        Box/Folder 27: 3
        See also: Subject file, war (Box 28, Folder 7).
      - Leopold von Wiese, 1950, undated
        Box/Folder 27: 4
      - Max Weber, 1941-1965, undated
        Box/Folder 27: 5-6
        See also: Notes on Max Weber (Box 26, Folder 8).
      - "Nature of the Social,", 1957, undated
        Box/Folder 27: 7
      - Science I, epistemological, 1951-1956
        Box/Folder 27: 8
      - Science II, 1956
        Box/Folder 27: 9
      - Science III, nature of the human realm, 1956, undated
        Box/Folder 27: 10
      - Social theory, period I, 1967, undated
        Box/Folder 27: 11
      - Social theory, period II, enlightenment, 1964, undated
        Box/Folder 27: 12
      - Social theory, period III, Comte, 1938-1973, undated (Reel 24)
        Box/Folder 28: 1
      - Sociological variables, 1950, undated
        Box/Folder 28: 2
      - Spencer (Herbert) polarity, 1971-1975, undated
        Box/Folder 28: 3
      - Spengler, Oswald, 1948-1979, undated
        Box/Folder 28: 4
        Includes notes on Arnold J. Toynbee.
      - Status of sociology, 1956-circa 1969, undated
        Box/Folder 28: 5
        Includes "On Humanistic Sociology" and other writings.
      - Subjectivity, 1960-1973, undated
        Box/Folder 28: 6
      - War, 1940-1943, undated
        Box/Folder 28: 7
        Includes "Basis of Personal Optimism" and notes on German militarism.
    - Writings with references to Abel, 1948-1976
      Box/Folder 28: 8
  - Printed matter, 1933-1988
    Includes monographs, journals, and reprints in English, German, and Polish.
    - English language material
      - General, 1934-1985
        Box/Folder 28: 9-10
      - General, 1933-1988, undated
        Box/Folder 28: 11
      - General (cont'd.), 1933-1988, undated (Reel 25)
        Box/Folder 29: 1-2
      - Papers by Willard Waller, undated
        Box/Folder 29: 3
      - Reprints, including on Max Weber, 1950-1964, undated
        Box/Folder 29: 4
    - German language material, 1933-1984 (Reel 26)
      Box/Folder 29: 5-6
    - Polish language material, 1935-1987
      Box/Folder 30: 1-3
    - Reprints, 1936-1973
      Box/Folder 30: 4
  - Damaged items, documents that appear to be book reviews by Abel
    Box/Folder 30: 5-6
    Due to preservation concerns, the items are not available for use.